Guide to the Edith Kramer Papers MC.215
New York University Archives
- Series II: Photographs and Slides, 178876; 2.5 Linear Feet
  - Late 70s- Early 80s Edith Kramer Artwork Slides, 1975, Undated; 180688 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Edith Kramer Artwork Slides, 1998-2000; 180689 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Drawing Watercolor Edith Kramer's Drawings and Watercolor Slides, 1972, Undated; 180690 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Sonia Patient Artwork Slides, Undated; 180691 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Demonstration II Artwork Slides, 1965-1966, Undated; 180692 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Sublimination Patient Artwork Slides & The Royal Library Slides, Undated; 180693 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Egg Tempera Edith Kramer Artwork Slides, 1975-1997; 180694 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Decarly Usaut Early Edith Kramer Artwork Slides, 1949-1990; 180695 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Jackson Patient Artwork Slides, Undated; 180696 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - [Redacted] Patient Artwork Slides, 1969, Undated; 180697 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Herman Patient Artwork Slides, 1968-1969, Undated; 180698 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Jacoby Spring 72 Patient Artwork Slides, 1972; 180699 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Jewish Guild/ Carciss at Guild Artwork Slides, 1969; 180700 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - L&W Blondie Patient Artwork Slides, 1959-1960; 180701 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Gabe 1978 Patient Artwork Slides, 1964-1965; 180702 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Pendergast & Misc. Wiltwyck Patient Artwork Slides, Undated; 180703 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Late 70s & 80s Edith Kramer Artwork Slides, 1979-1987; 180704 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Ray 64/65 Patient Artwork Slides, 1964-1965; 180705 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Chapters 1,8, and 9 Note,s Copies, and Photographs, Undated; 180314 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 7 and 10 Copies with Notes and Photographs, Undated; 180326 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chapters 11, 12, and 16 Notes, Copies, and Photographs, Undated; 180327 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Chapters 15, 18, and 20 Notes, Copies, and Photographs, Undated; 180329 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Edith's Photos (1), 1925-1993, Undated; 180330 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Edith's Photos (2), 1997-1998, Undated; 180333 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of Friedl Dicker-Brandeis, Undated; 181014 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Photo Negatives and Contact Sheets, Undated; 180334 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dwayne and Friends Photos and Artwork (9W), Undated; 180335 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Patient Artwork Photographs, 1965-1968; 180337 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Patient Artwork Photographs, 1964-1966, Undated; 180339 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Patient Artwork Photographs, 1965-1969, Undated; 180342 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Patient Artwork Photographs, 1966-1968, Undated; 180343 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Unidentified Children, Undated; 180344 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs from Edith Kramer Exhibit, 1997; 180345 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mountain Cabin Studio Photos, Grundlsee Austria, 2004, Undated; 180347 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photos of Carliss, Blind Child in Claymaking, Undated; 180349 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Edith Kramer Artwork Prints, 1980-2002; 180350 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Edith Kramer's Artwork, 1984-2001; 180351 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Black and White Photographs of Edith Kramer's Paintings and Sculptures, 1938-1992; 180352 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Edith Kramer Artwork Photos, Postcards, and Prints, 1972-1992, Undated; 180353 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Invitation Photos, 1994-1996; 180355 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Series III: Personal Papers, 178874; 1 Linear Feet
  This series consists mainly of personal correspondence, most of which is in English and some of which is in German. There is also information Edith Kramer compiled about the Bosket family, a family of professional interest to Kramer, as well as short, handwritten autobiographical narratives written by Edith Kramer. The series also contains a number of Edith Kramer's date books.
  - Pocket Date Books, 1949-1951; 180011 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Official Class Roll Book, 1984-1991; 180013 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Assignments & Dates to Remember, 1981-1982; 180015 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Datebooks, 1998-2001; 180016 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Datebooks, 2001-2006; 180018 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: A-C, 1949-1999; 180031 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: D-G, 1949-2000; 180049 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: H-J, 1938, 1992, Undated; 181046 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: K-M, 1950-2002; 180052 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: N-P, 1948,1973,1995; 180055 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Q-S, 1949-1993; 180056 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: T-Z, 1950-1996; 180057 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: General A-I, 1949-2003; 180058 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: General J-P, 1950, 1990, 1996, Undated; 180059 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: General Q-Z, 1948-1985; 180060 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: General- Unisgned, 1949-1972; 180061 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Dr. Bernard (mentor), 1950; 180062 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Ingred B. Hansson, 1998-2006; 180063 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Von Ewer Schwurstenn Heidrun, 2001-2003; 180064 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Peter Heller, 1986-1996; 180065 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Jeanne/J, 1945-1998; 180066 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Lena, 1981-1992; 180067 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Liesl, Undated, 1946, 1951; 180068 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Nizie, 1949-1952; 180069 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Emily Nelligan, Undated; 180070 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: Hazel & Mark Peper, 1948-1949; 180071 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: Sandra Pine, 1980; 180072 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: Heidrun Pupp, Undated; 180073 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: Sally, 1948-1950; 180074 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Schocken Books, 1962-1975; 180075 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: Elizabeth Sifton, 1948-1950; 180076 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: Sigga, 1985-1999; 180077 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: Bernice Thompson, 1947-1948; 180078 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence: Russerln Dein, 1936-1949; 180079 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence: Elinor Ulman, 1958-1967; 180080 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence: Random/Assorted, 1993, 1999, Undated; 180081 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Papers on William Butch Bosket Sr., 1980-1983; 180082 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Papers on William James Bosket Jr., 1987-1992; 180083 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Papers from All God's Children: The Bosket Family, 1993-1995; 180084 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Unidentified Artwork, 1957, Undated; 181038 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Litte Red School House: A Chronicle of 75 Years, 1996; 181039 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Edith Kramer Artwork Papers and Catalogue, 1938-1996; 181040 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscript Pages and Notes, Undated; 181043 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Art Therapy in a Children's Community Noted Book Jacket Manuscript, Undated; 181047 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Edith Kramer's Handwritten Autobiographical Narratives, Undated; 181049 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Patient's Handwritten Narrative with Contributions from Edith Kramer, Undated; 181050 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Assorted Mailings from Art and Art Therapy Associations, 1975, 1994, 1998, Undated; 181051 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Document, 1941-1985; 181052 (Box 8, Folder 48)
- Series IV: Audiovisual Material, 180706
  This series consists of audiovisual materials and electronic records. Included within this series are CDs of photographs of Edith Kramer's artwork and of her trips to Austria. There are also video recordings of lectures from her course "Psychodynamic Processes in Art Therapy." There are also several audio recordings that include interviews of Kramer and recordings of presentations she gave at meetings of the American Art Therapy Association.
  Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
  Not all the audiovisual materials in this series have been digitized, and audiovisual materials may not be used in their original formats. Please contact the University Archives to gain access to these materials. Be aware that it may take several weeks to have audiovisual materials digitized for access.
  The videocassettes depicting Edith Kramer's course "Psycho Dynamic Processes in Art Therapy" have already been digitized. Please contact the Archives for access.
  - Edith Kramer Artwork, 2010, undated; 180707; 1 electronic discs (cd-rom) (Box 9, Disc 1)
    This disc contains over 200 digital images of Edith Kramer's works of art.
  - Edith Kramer Biographical Photographs, 2010, undated; 180708; 1 electronic discs (cd-rom) (Box 9, Disc 2)
  - Edith Kramer Weiss Galley Photographs, 2010, undated; 180709; 1 electronic discs (cd-rom) (Box 9, Disc 3)
  - Edith Kramer Psychodynamic Processes In Art Therapy Lectures, 2006; 180714; 10 videocassettes (Box 9, Cassette 4-13)
    General note
    The 10 tapes comprising this item used to be cataloged as individual items with unique identifiers. They were ref283-292. Now are all contained within this item (ref 283).
    Scope and Contents
    Ten lectures on Psychodynamic Process in Art Therapy.
    Access copies
    Access copies available on 10 DVDs: ACCESS 9:34 - ACCESS 9:43
  - Edith Kramer Lecture on her Work at the New York Transit Museum, 1 March 1994; 180724; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 50 minutes (Box 9, Cassette 14)
    Access copy
    Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:26
    This recording features a talk Edith Kramer gave at the New York Transit Museum on March 1, 1994. Her lecture was a feature of her own exhibition that was on display there at the time, and a celebration at the beginning of Women's History Month. The exhibition featured subway-related art Kramer had created between 1940 and 1994. She discusses her artwork and life in New York City.
    The event is apparently sparsely attended as the Museum Curator Tom Harrington says in his opening remarks, "the world's situation has kept the crowd down to just a few." He does not specify what situation he means, but it is possible he is referring to the shooting attack on a bus full of Orthodox Jewish students that had taken place on the Brooklyn Bridge that morning, which would eventually result the death of 16-year-old Ari Halberstam. At the time of this recording, the shooter, Rashid Baz, was still at large.
    Art.; subway trains; Subway stations.; Subways in art; Subways.; Artists.; Art -- Study and teaching.; Art therapy.
  - Das Lied Ist Aus/Elisabeth Neuman-Viertel, May 1988; 180727; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 50 minutes (Box 9, Cassette 15, Box Access 10, Item 31)
    Content is entirely in German. "Das Lied ist aus" is the original title of a 1930 German film. The title translated into English as The Song Is Ended. Elisabeth Neuman-Viertel was a German actress. While she was active at that time, she was not in the cast. Neuman-Viertel was active at the time of these recordings and was in a 1988 film entitled, Wie kommt das Salz ins Meer? The beginnings of both sides is identical, a female voice speaking in German fading out as the sound of goose-stepping soldiers fades in. Based on this identical content, the consecutive dates and the serial notation of "parts 3 and 4," these are probably recordings of two episodes of a radio show of some kind, possibly focusing on 1930's German cinema. Without the ability to translate, it is impossible to tell.
    Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:31
    Film.
  - Gauz Ich Daheim be Edith Kramer, 11 July 2003; 180728; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 15 minutes (Box 9, Cassette 16, Box Access 10, Item 32)
    Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:32.
    Recording is in German. It begins with a brief piece of music and introduction by a male voice. This is followed by a woman speaking, saying something in German about New York City. Possibly a radio program.
  - Austrian Heritage Collection Oral History Interview with Edith Kramer, 2005 April 13; 180729; 2 sound cassettes Approx. 80 minutes (Box 9, Cassette 17-18, Box Access 10, Item 29-30)
    Austrian Heritage Collection oral history interview with Edith Kramer conducted on April 13, 2005.
    Access copy available on 2 CDS: ACCESS 10:29 & ACCESS 10:30
  - Quality And Inner Satisfaction: Revisiting The Importance Of Quality In Art And Art Therapy, November, 2001; 180731; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 64 minutes (Box 9, Cassette 19, Box Access 10, Item 33)
    Scope and content
    Edith Kramer does not appear on this recording, which represents a plenary presentation at the annual conference for the American Art Therapy Association. Her lecture is read by the other participants. Participants include Susan Ainlay Anand and Lani A. Gerity. The tape was produced by the American Art Therapy Association, Inc.
    Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:33
  - Cultural Humility: Recognizing Wisdom, Hope, and Beauty in the Cultural Fringes, 2002; 180732; 1 sound cassettes (Box 9, Cassette 20, Box Access 10, Item 34)
    This recording represents a panel discussion at the annual conference of the American Art Therapy Association, in which Edith Kramer participates. Other participants include Lani Gerity, Martha Haeseler, and Susan Anand. The tape was produced by the American Art Therapy Association, Inc.
    Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:34
  - Unexpected Gifts: A Discussion of Culture, Time and the Artist's Second Wind, 2000; 180733; 1 sound cassettes (Box 9, Cassette 21)
  - "Elena", 29 October 2009; 181053; 1 electronic discs (cd-rom) (Box 9, Disc 27)
- Series V: Artwork, 1937-2000
  This series includes two sub-series. Subseries A includes artwork created by Edith Kramer throughout her life. Subseries B includes artwork created by Kramer and her patients during the course of art therapy.
  - Sub-Series A: Artwork by Edith Kramer, 1937-1993; 178879
    Sub-Series A contains examples of Edith Kramer's artwork. These works highlight Kramer's development as an artist and her work in a variety of mediums, including sculpture, oil paintings, watercolors, collages, and pencil sketches. Of particular note is a sketchbook that includes pencil drawings inspired by the French Revolution that Kramer completed as a child. Many of the images depict industrial settings, subway stations or riders, and landscapes. Also included within the collection are a number of self-portraits completed at various ages. This series also encompasses sketches she completed of her fellow employees at the machine shop in which she worked during World War II.
    - Montana Larches (Oil on Canvas), Undated; 200183 (Bin 1, Item 1)
    - Untitled [Faces] (Oil on Canvas), Undated; cuid258; 200184; 1 item one painting (Item MC.215.cuid258)
      Paintings (visual works)
    - Mountain Larch (Oil on Canvas), 1975; cuid259; 200185; 1 item one painting (Item MC.215.cuid259)
    - Landscape with Haystack (Oil on Canvas), 1938; cuid260; 200186; 1 item one painting (Item MC.215.cuid260)
    - Larches in Fog (Oil on Canvas), 1980; cuid261; 200187; 1 item one painting (Item MC.215.cuid261)
    - Railway Track in Prague (Oil on Canvas), Undated; cuid262; 200188; 1 item one painting (Item MC.215.cuid262, Item 6)
    - Self Portrait (Oil on Canvas), 1938; 200189 (Bin 1, Item 7)
    - Cathedral of Ameins (Oil on Canvas), 1949; cuid263; 200191; 1 item one painting (Item MC.215.cuid263)
    - [Untitled Collage] (Mixed Materials, Wood Frame), 1949; 200192 (Bin 1, Item 9)
    - Kramer Childhood Artwork The French Revolution: A Homemade Storyboard, 1930; 200239 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 1)
    - Subway Riders, 1945; 200245 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 1, Item 11-181i)
    - Subway Illustration, 1992; 200246 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 1, Item 11-182oo)
    - Subway Illustration, Undated; 200248 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 1, Item 11-182pp)
    - Subway Illustration, Undated; 200249 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 1, Item 11-182uu)
    - Subway Illustration, Undated; 200250 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 1, Item 11-182ww)
    - Mosaic Mural Poster, 1993; 200251 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 1, Item 11-182xx)
    - From Bauhaus to Terezin poster, 1989; 200252 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 1, Item 11-182zz)
    - Mosaic Tile Sample Proposal for Chambers Street Station, 1993; 200253 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-182xx)
    - Subway Rider Sketch, 1987; 200254 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-186k)
    - Subway Riders, 1986; 200255 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-186l)
    - Subway Illustration, Undated; 200279 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-182aaa)
    - Subway Illustration, Undated; 200280 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-182aaa)
    - Subway Illustration, Undated; 200281 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-182aaa)
    - Subway Watercolor, 1993; 200282 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-18299)
    - Subway Watercolor, 1992; 200283 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-182rr)
    - Subway Pencil Sketch, 1987; 200284 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-182tt)
    - Subway Pencil Sketch, 1988; 200285 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-182vv)
    - Subway Pencil Sketch, Undated; 200571 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-182ss)
    - Subway Pencil Sketch, 1945; 200574 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-182yy)
    - Pastel Self Portrait, Undated; 200575 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-227d)
    - Untitled Photostat, Undated; 200576 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-228uu)
    - Edith Kramer Tribute Poster, 2005; 200577 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2)
    - Landscape Illustration, 1953; 200578 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-186j)
    - Landscape Illustration, 1978; 200579 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-186i)
    - Petrified River Weiderkar Aus., 1981; 200580 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 2, Item 11-186h)
    - Machinery at Carl Schleicher's Shope, 1947; 200581 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-181l)
    - Machinist Detail, 1948; 200582 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-181k)
    - Machinist Drawing, 1947; 200583 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-181n)
    - Machinist Drawing, 1947; 200584 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-181m)
    - Landscape Sketch, Undated; 200585 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-2288)
    - Man Sketch, Undated; 200586 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-2286)
    - Sketch of a Woman, Undated; 200587 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228p)
    - Fridl Dicker, 1937; 200588 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-227b)
    - Untitled Print, Undated; 200589 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228b)
    - Sketch of a Woman "Grundlsee", 1937; 200590 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228ll)
    - Bench Sketch, 1959; 200591 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228m)
    - Sketch of a Woman, Undated; 200594 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228e)
    - Subway Riders Sketch, Undated; 200595 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228g)
    - Sketch in Pen, Undated; 200596 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228w)
    - Sketch of a Couple, 1940; 200597 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-227c)
    - Sketch of Ship, Undated; 200598 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228aa)
    - Self Portrait, 1937; 200599 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-227a)
    - Medieval Sketch, 1937/1938; 200600 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228t)
    - Pencil Sketch, 1938; 200601 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228l)
    - St. Zorenz, Verona, 1985; 200602 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228mm)
    - Park Sketch, Undated; 201411 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-22866)
    - Sleeping Person Sketch, Undated; 201412 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-2287)
    - German Booklet, Undated; 201413 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228ii)
    - Landscape Sketch, Undated; 201414 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-229qq)
    - Pencil Sketch, Undated; 201415 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228nn)
    - Floral Print, Undated; 201416 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228ww)
    - Machinist Sketch, 1943; 201417 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228kk)
    - Man Sketch, 1959; 201418 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228f)
    - Machinist Sketch, 1944; 201419 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228a)
    - City Sketch, 1950; 201420 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 1-228cc)
    - Caravaggio Sketch, Undated; 201421 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228x)
    - Sleeping Man Sketch, 1948; 201422 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228e)
    - Print, Undated; 201423 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228c)
    - Print, Undated; 201424 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228k)
    - Print, Undated; 201425 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228jj)
    - Print, 1954; 201426 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228j)
    - Caravaggio Sketch, Undated; 201427 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228dd)
    - Pencil Sketch, Undated; 201428 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228w)
    - Pencil Sketch, Undated; 201429 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228y)
    - Headless Sketch, Undated; 201430 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228ee)
    - Insbruck Sketch, 1980; 201431 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228v)
    - Mary and Jesus Sketch, Undated; 201432 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228gg)
    - Sketch, Undated; 201433 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228u)
    - 1440 Brixen Sketch, Undated; 201434 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228hh)
    - Landscape Watercolor, Undated; 201435 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228xx)
    - Statue Sketch, Undated; 201436 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228h)
    - Church Window Sketch, Undated; 201437 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228i)
    - Pencil Sketch, 1938; 201438 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228s)
    - Pencil Sketch, 1938; 201439 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228ff)
    - Industrial Landscape, 1953; 201440 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228pp)
    - Floral Drawing, Undated; 201441 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228ss)
    - Construction Watercolor, 1947; 201442 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228rr)
    - Landscape Watercolor, 1982; 201443 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228oo)
    - Cathedral d'Amiens Paris, 1948; 201444 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228tt)
    - Dinosaur Fossil Print, 1946; 201445 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 3, Item 11-228yy)
    - Girl Drawing, 1937; cuid264; 1 item one painting (Item MC.215.cuid264)
    - Self-portrait, 1983; cuid265; 1 item one painting (Item MC.215.cuid265)
    - Collage, 1941; cuid266; 1 item one collage (Item MC.215.cuid266)
      Collages (visual works)
    - Mountain Larches, Undated; cuid257; 1 item one painting (Item MC.215.cuid257)
    - Untitled [Woman on bench], Undated; cuid267; 1 item one sculpture (Item MC.215.cuid267)
      Sculpture (visual works)
    - Untitled [People and trees], Undated; cuid268; 1 item one sculpture (Item MC.215.cuid268)
    - Untitled [Woman in bathtub], Undated; cuid269; 1 item one sculpture (Item MC.215.cuid269)
    - Untitled [Ceramic pitcher with figures and trees], Undated; cuid270; 1 item one pitcher (Item MC.215.cuid270)
      pitchers (vessels)
    - Forsythe Park with Trees Collage, 1969 (Flat-file-folder 11)
      Collage with paper and newsprint measuring 38 1/4" high by 42 1/4" wide.
  - Sub-Series B: Artwork Created During Art Therapy, 1951-2000
    All artworks in this sub-series were created during art therapy with Edith Kramer. The majority were created by patients, but some were created by Kramer as examples to show patients. Titles in brackets are descriptions of untitled works.
    Biographical / Historical
    Over the course of her career Edith Kramer worked as an art therapist at various institutions in the New York City metro area.
    Kramer worked at the Wiltwyck School for Boys in the 1940s and 1950s. This school was founded by the Episcopal City Mission Society in 1936 as a school and residential treatment facility for Black boys who were diverted from the juvenile justice system. In 1942 the Episcopal City Mission Society announced it could no longer financially support Wiltwyck and group of concerned citizens including Eleanor Roosevelt recognized the value of the school and banded together to fund the school and reorganize it under the State Department of Social Welfare. After the reorganization the school was non-secular and racially integrated, and in 1953 Wiltwyck began to accept students with severe emotional needs.